Guide to Hellmut Juretschke Papers RG.049
Poly Archives at the Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology, NYU Libraries
Hellmut Juretschke Papers
1926-2018
Poly Archives at the Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology, NYU Libraries
Juretschke, Hellmut J., 1924-2019
RG.049
10 Linear Feet
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated to the Poly Archives by Hellmut Juretschke's daughters, Annette Juretschke Cavajal and Susan Juretschke in February 2022.
Arrangement
This collection is housed in fourteen boxes and arranged into six series: Series I: Academia, 1929-2016 Series II: Brooklyn Poly, 1950-2013 Series III: Instruction, 1985-1997 Series IV: Papers and Conferences, 1941-2018 Series V: Paul Peter Ewald, 1926-2015 and Series VI: Publications, 1953-2018. Original order was maintained whenever possible. However, there was some reorganization of materials for series placement.
Biographical / Historical
Hellmut J. Juretschke was born in Berlin, Germany on August 9, 1924. He earned his PhD from Harvard University and later served as Head of the Physics Department at the Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn, where he earned the distinction of Professor Emeritus. Professor Juretschke's affiliation with the Institute dates back to 1950, when he started his teaching career as Instructor. His scientific interests included crystal physics, surface properties, and electronic structure of metals. After retiring from a career as a physicist, Juretschke published several works of poetry and translation. He passed away in 2019.
Scope and Contents
The Hellmut Juretschke Papers contain documents from 1926 to 2018. These documents were assembled by Juretschke throughout his professional career at Brooklyn Poly (operating under the names of Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn (1900-1973), Polytechnic Institute of New York (1973-1985), Polytechnic University (1985-2008), and Polytechnic Institute of New York University). The collection contains professional writings and publications as well as personal writings such as letters and poems. Documents include books, journals, notes, correspondence, papers, and reprints. The collection is 10 linear feet, located on bay 29, shelves 4E-7E. While the NYU Poly Archives houses Juretshcke's professional papers, a donation of his family papers can be found at the Jewish Museum Berlin.
Polytechnic University (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; Physics; Reprints; Photographs; Audiovisual materials; Poetry; Books; Ewald, Paul Peter, 1888-1985
- Series I: Academia, 1929-2016
  - Sub-series A: Books, 1929-1990
    - Corresp. re: How to Solve Problems and Washington Post Editorial, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - How to Solve Problems by Donald Scarl, 1990 (Box 1, Item 1)
    - International Conference on Physics Vol. II The Solid State of Matter, 1935 (Box 1, Item 2)
    - Theory of X-Ray Diffraction in Crystals by William H. Zachariasen, 1945 (Box 1, Item 3)
    - Introduction to Modern Physics by F. K. Richtmyer & E. H. Kennard, 1942 (Box 1, Item 4)
    - The Dynamics of Conduction Electrons by A. B. Pippard, 1965 (Box 1, Item 5)
    - A Short Table of Integrals by B.O. Peirce, 1929 (Box 1, Item 6)
    - The Physics of Dance by Kenneth Laws, 1984 (Box 1, Item 7)
    - Feier der 100, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Lebensgeschichte von Otto Blumenthal, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Zum Phasenproblem der Rontgenstruktuanalyse by Edgar Weckert, 1988 (Box 1, Item 8)
    - Ekuador: Die Wundervolle Werkstatt Der Natur by Dr. Ing. Richard F. A. Muller, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Aus Kossels Laboratorium and Letter, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - X-Ray Diffraction Studies of Acoustoelectrically Amplified Phonon Beams by S. LeRoux, 1978 (Box 1, Item 9)
    - A Dictionary of Science by E. B. Uvarov and D. R. Chapman, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sub-series B: Colleagues and Other Scholars, 1955-2007
    - R. Landauer, 1955-2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - G. Hildebrandt, 1982-2003 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - C. Darwin, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - W. L. Bragg, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Martin Brinn, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - H. Wegenfeld, 1969-2007 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - H. E. Laue, 1969-2004 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Sub-series C: Correspondence, 1963-2015
    - Miscellaneous Emails from H. Juretschke's Computer, 2014-2015 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Greenoble - 1964 Sabbatical, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Australia 1985 Visiting Fellow - Physics, 1979-1985 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Sub-series D: Journals, 1980-1998
    - Corresp. re: Crystal Research and Technology, 1998-05-19 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Crystal Research and Technology Vol. 33, No. 4 edited by G. Hildebrandt, 1998 (Box 3, Item 1)
    - Australian Journal of Physics Special Issue Vol. 41, No. 3, 1988 (Box 3, Item 2)
    - Acta Historica Leopoldina Number 14 1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Crystallography Reviews Vol.1, No. 2 edited by Moreton Moore, 1987 (Box 3, Item 3)
  - Sub-series E: Notes, 1979-1998
    - X-ray Photon Interaction Calc., 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 3-Beam Calculations, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Modified 2-Beam Calculations, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Surface EMW - Work, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Noncentric 222, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Sub-series F: Personal Papers, 1942-1996
    - Harvard University, 1942-1949 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Veterans Admin., 1946-1965 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Occasional Scientific Correspondence, 1971-1996 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Outside Work, 1961-1989 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Fellowships and Job Offers, 1950-1974 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Harvard - Bell Labs Correspondence (Lester Germer), 1948-1950 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Sub-series G: Scholarly Articles, 1966-2016
    - Article Reprints on Thermal Diffuse X-ray Scattering, 1972-1982 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Article Reprints on Surface-Plasmon Dispersion, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Article Reprints on X-ray Reflection Phases, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Article Reprints on Crystals, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Article Reprints on Surface Stress, 1966-1977 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Manitoba 2016 - Spin Rectification (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Sub-series H: Tapes, undated
    - TDK Video Cassette from Royal Melbourne Institute of Tech. Dept. of Applied Physics, undated (Box 4, Item 1)
- Series II: Brooklyn Poly, 1950-2013
  - Sub-series A: Administrative, 1950-2006
    - Professorial Papers, 1950-1995 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Retirement, 1986-2006 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Albany Success, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Sub-series B: Dissertations and Theses, 1950-1993
    - Untersuchungen zur Phasenmessung by Wolfgang Schwegle, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - The Surface Energy and Surface Structure of Metals by Hellmut J. Juretschke, 1950 (Box 4, Item 2)
    - Doctoral Committee Theses, 1964-1993 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Field Effect in Semiconductors by Andrea J. Alotta, 1963-06 (Box 4, Item 3)
    - Electrical Properties of Phthalocyanines by Jacques Assour, 1962-06 (Box 4, Item 4)
    - The Hall Effect and Ferromagnetism of Thin Nickel Films by Richard Coren, 1956-06 (Box 5, Item 1)
    - Surface Influences in the Metallic Field Effect by Charles Dancak, 1969-06 (Box 5, Item 2)
    - The Surface Resistance of Superconducting Electroplated Lead at 9030 MC by Peter K. Shizume, 1959-06 (Box 5, Item 3)
    - Harmonic Generation Through Galvanomagnetic Interactions in Ferromagnetic Resonance by Howard Stark, 1966-06 (Box 5, Item 4)
    - Some Ferromagnetic Resonance Experiments at "X" - Band Frequencies by Sheldon L. Trubatch, 1962-06 (Box 5, Item 5)
    - Strain Effect on Silver Film Resistivity by Bhullan Singh Verma, 1969-06 (Box 5, Item 6)
  - Sub-series C: Faculty/Student Employment, 1950-1998
    - Arnold, Steve, 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Abstracts for Hellmut, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Polytechnic University Binder - Arnold, Steve CV, 1995 (Box 5, Item 7)
    - Student Letters of Recommendation, 1968-1993 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Employment at Polytechnic Institute - Juretschke, 1950-1990 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Poly H. Juretschke - Staff - Letters of Recommendation, 1966-1998 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Sub-series D: Honors and Awards, 1972-1992
    - Polytechnic University Plaque for 40 Years of Service, 1990 (Box 6, Item 1)
    - Plaque from 80th Pct. Youth Council, 1972 (Box 6, Item 2)
    - Physics Alumni Convocation, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Sub-series E: Memorabilia, undated
    - MicroParticle PhotoPhysics Laboratory T-shirt, undated (Box 6, Item 3)
  - Sub-series F: Photographs, 1968-1998
    - Polytechic Institute of New York Binder, 1968-1977 (Box 7, Item 1)
    - Photographs, 1977-1998 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Sub-series G: Publications, 1966-2013
    - Polytechnic People, 1971-2013 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Misc. Articles, Journals, and Memoranda, 1966-2008 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Series III: Instruction, 1985-1997
  - Sub-series A: Calculation Notes, 1993-1997
    - 2 S = 0 Calculations, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - 3 S > 1 Calculations, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - 4 Calculations, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - 5 Misc. Side Calculations, 1993-1994 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - 6 Old Calc., 1994 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - 7 Calculations, 1995-1996 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - 8 Calculations, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - 9 Calculations, 1995-1997 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - 10 Calculations, undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - 11 Cross Polarization Calculations, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - 12 Calculations, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Analysis of Cir-in Lin-out Curves, undated (Box 8, Item 1)
  - Sub-series B: Curriculum, 1985-1993
    - Computer-Assisted Instruction (CAI) in Physics Research, 1985-1989 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Physics Course Notes and Correspondence, 1990-1992 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Ch.5 Analysis and CAI Progress Report, 1988-1992 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Ch.5 Homework, 1987-1992 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - CAI Physics Program Proposal and Articles, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - CAI Analysis, 1988-1993 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Papers and Conferences, 1941-2018
  - Sub-series A: Conferences, 1986-2002
    - Bordeaux - IUCr Microsymposium, 1989-1990 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Surface Field Talk, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - American Assoc. for the Advancement of Science 1995 Annual Meeting 1, 1994-2002 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - American Assoc. for the Advancement of Science 1995 Binder, 1994-1995 (Box 8, Item 2)
    - American Assoc. for the Advancement of Science 1995 Annual Meeting 2, 1994-1995 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - American Assoc. for the Advancement of Science 1995 View Graphs and Outline, 1994-1995 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Dynamical N-Beam Theory of X-Rays, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Sub-series B: Papers, 1941-2018
    - Determination of Invariant X-ray Structure Factor Phases Abstract and Science Journal, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Misc. - Technical Reports, Physics Notes, Corresp., 1957-1998 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Crystal Optics and Dynamical Theory Viewgraphs, 1990-1998 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1941-2012 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Unpublished Manuscripts, 2001-2018 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Series V: Paul Peter Ewald, 1926-2015
  - Sub-series A: Books, 1933-1993
    - Die Erforschung Des Aufbaus Der Materie Mit Roentgenstrahlen Index, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Die Erforschung Des Aufbaus Der Materie Mit Roentgenstrahlen by P. P. Ewald, 1933 (Box 9, Item 1)
    - P. P. Ewald and his Dynamical Theory of X-ray Diffraction ed. by H. J. Juretschke, 1992 (Box 10, Item 1)
    - P. P. Ewald and his Dynamical Theory of X-ray Diffraction Advice Note, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Sub-series B: Correspondence, 1926-2015
    - Correspondence re: Paul Peter Ewald Memorial Volume 1, 1989-1993 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence re: Paul Peter Ewald Memorial Volume 2, 1990-1991 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence re: Paul Peter Ewald Memorial Volume 3, 1987-1991 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence to Prof. Bohren re: Ewald-Oseen Publications, 1987-1992 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - American Journal of Physics - Ewald-Oseen Comments 1, 1998-1999 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - American Journal of Physics - Ewald-Oseen Comments 2, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Hildebrandt Correspondence re: Ewald, 1990-1991 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence re: American Crystallographic Assoc., 1985-1992 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Corresp. re: International Conference on Physics and Ewald, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Ewald - Personal Letters, Poems, etc., 1960-2014 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Ewald-Arnold Ella Etc. Emails, 2009-2015 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Ewald - Klapper, undated (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Letters and Reprints About Paul Peter Ewald, 1926-1990 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Sub-series C: Lectures, 1951-1987
    - P. P. E Lecture Notes and Mayer Thesis, 1951-1979 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Perth-Ewald Viewgraphs and Lecture, 1966-1987 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Sub-series D: Other Publications, 1937-1990
    - Ewald I - Reprints, 1937-1938 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Ewald II - Reprints, 1937-1938 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - P. P. E Book Reviews, 1949-1959 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - P. P. E Bibliography, 1988-1990 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Ewald III - Reprints, 1967-1974 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Physics Today September 1974 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - On the Foundations of Crystal Optics by P. P. Ewald, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Acta Crystallographica P. P. Ewald Memorial Issue, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Sub-series E: Tapes, undated
    - Paul P. Ewald - Recording Poem for Dr. John Dropkin, undated (Box 11, Item 1)
- Series VI: Publications, 1953-2018
  - Sub-series A: Books, 1974-1992
    - Crystal Physics by Hellmut J. Juretschke, 1974 (Box 12, Item 1)
    - On the Foundations of Crystal Optics ed. by Hellmut J. Juretschke, 1991 (Box 12, Item 2)
    - On the Foundations of Crystal Optics Forms, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Sub-series B: Correspondence, 1953-2016
    - Correspondence re: "Crystal Physics" by Hellmut Juretschke, 1976-1990 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Crystal Physics re: Dover Publications, 1978-1993 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence I, 1953-2016 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence II, 1998 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Sub-series C: Poetry and Memoir, 2013-2018
    - H. Juretschke Poems, 2018 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Rereading Rilke by Hellmut J. Juretschke, 2015 (Box 12, Item 3)
    - After 08/80: Some 21 Poems & Several Translations by Hellmut J. Juretschke, 2013 (Box 12, Item 4)
    - The Hopeless Garden: Misc. Poems & More Translations by Hellmut J. Juretschke, 2015 (Box 12, Item 5)
    - Glimpses of a Boyhood in Troubled Times by Hellmut J. Juretschke, 2017 (Box 12, Item 6)
  - Sub-series D: Scholarly Articles, 1960-1991
    - Acta Cryst. Article on First Order Solution and Graphs, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Publications, Reprints, and Drafts, 1970-1991 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Acta Cryst. Article on Thermal Phonons, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Australian Journals of Scientific Research Reprint Article, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Article Reprints and Draft on Beam Reflections, 1982-1988 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Crystal Physics with Solutions pg. 207-323, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Problems in Crystal Physics with Solutions I, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Reprints and Lists, 1960-1988 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Binder - H. Juretschke Prints in Order, undated (Box 13, Item 1)
    - References to Early Work, 1962-1979 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Problems in Crystal Physics with Solutions II, 1978 (Box 14, Item 1)